JOSHUA S. SPEAGLE

Statistical Sciences, Astronomy & Astrophysics, Dunlap Institute University of Toronto

joshspeagle.github.io | j.speagle@utoronto.ca

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie in the interdisciplinary fields of **astrostatistics** and **data science** at the intersections of statistics, astronomy, and computer science. I develop methods and analyse large datasets to better understand how galaxies like our own **Milky Way** form, behave, and evolve.

POSITIONS

Banting & Dunlap Postdoctoral Fellow: University of Toronto	2020-present
Joint between Statistical Sciences, Astronomy & Astrophysics, & the Dunlap Institute	
Supervisor: Gwen Eadie	
Project Academic Support Staff: Kavli IPMU, University of Tokyo	2015-2016
Supervisors: Naoki Yoshida, Alexie Leauthaud (UCSC), & Kevin Bundy (UCSC)	

EDUCATION

Harvard University: PhD in Astronomy	2016-2020
Advisers: Doug Finkbeiner, Charlie Conroy, Daniel Eisenstein, & Alyssa Goodman	
Harvard University: MA in Astronomy	2016-2020
Advisers: Daniel Eisenstein & Alexie Leauthaud (UCSC)	
Harvard University: BA in Astrophysics and Physics	2011-2015

AWARDS & HONORS

Best Astrostatistics Student Paper Award (ASA/AIG)	2020
Eric R. Keto Prize for Best Thesis in Theoretical Astrophysics (Harvard)	2020
Banting Postdoctoral Fellowship (Canada)	2020
Department of Astronomy Teaching Award (Harvard)	Spring 2018
Bok Center Certificate of Distinction in Teaching (Harvard)	Spring 2017, 18; Fall 2018
NSF Graduate Research Fellowship (USA)	2016

TEACHING

I have a strong interest in education and pedagogy, with a focus on skills such as **programming**, **statistics**, **and data science**. See my <u>teaching statement</u> for additional details.

EQUITY, DIVERSITY, & INCLUSION

I am committed to improving equity, diversity, and inclusion (EDI) in the classroom, in my work, and in the wider academic community. See my **EDI statement** for additional details.

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

An Introduction to Dynamic Nested Sampling

Web Director	2020-present
Astrostatistics Interest Group (American Statistical Association)	
Steering Committee Member	2020-present
Working Group on Astroinformatics & Astrostatistics (American Astronomical Society)	
Journal Clubs	2020
Co-Founder: Statistics & Machine Learning Journal Club (University of Toronto)	2020-present
Co-Organizer: astro-ph Coffee (University of Toronto) Founder: Center for Astrophysics Machine Learning Journal Club (Harvard University)	2020-present 2017-2020
Manuscript Referee	2017-2020
Journal of Open Source Software	2020-present
Astronomy & Astrophysics	2017-present
Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society	2016-present
American Astronomical Society Journals	2014-present
SELECTED PRESENTATIONS	
University of Florida: Colloquium	September 2020
Enabling Data-Driven Discovery in the Milky Way and Beyond Using Large Astronomic	al Datasets
Astro Hack Week 2020: Tutorial Leader	August 2020
Introduction to Bayesian Inference with Linear Regression	
Villanova: Colloquium	October 2019
Exploring the Galaxy Near and Far in the Age of Gaia	
Harvard: Summer Colloquium (joint with Catherine Zucker) Charting Nearby Molecular Clouds with Gaia: A New Map of Our Local Interstellar Me	June 2019 Edium
GitHub Satellite 2019: Keynote Address Participant	May 2019
Invited for open source code contributions (dynesty) in the analysis of the supermassive black Even Horizon Telescope collaboration	hole in M87 by the
University of Toronto: Special Seminar Photometric Distances Near and Far in the Age of Gaia	April 2019
Max Planck Institute for Astronomy: Galaxy Coffee The Devil's in the Detail's: Photometric Biases in Modern Surveys	April 2019
Cambridge: Data Intensive Science Seminar Mapping the 3-D Distribution of Dust in the Milky Way with Stellar Photometry	April 2019
Harvard: CMSA Big Data Conference Revealing the Milky Way's Dust-iny	August 2018
U Mass Amherst : Data Science Tea Big Data Inference: Combining Hierarchical Bayes and Machine Learning to Improve Phot	October 2017 tometric Redshifts
	September 2017

Kavli IPMU: Astronomy Lunch Seminar

Mapping, Visualizing, and Exploiting the Color-Redshift Relation

University of Tsukuba: Theoretical Astrophysics Seminar

The Evolution of Star-Forming Galaxies over Cosmic Time

August 2013

March 2016

PUBLICATIONS

I am an author of 48 papers that have over 2600 citations (h-index=17). This includes:

10 papers as (co-)first author (in red) with over 900 citations (h-index=7)

15 papers with substantial contributions (in blue) with over 400 citations (h-index=9)

Most of my papers can be found online on <u>arxiv</u> and <u>ADS</u>. My ORCID is <u>0000-0003-2573-9832</u>.

In Preparation

48. Zucker, C.; Goodman, A. G.; Alves, J.; Shmuel, B.; Koch, E.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Foley, M.; & Finkbeiner, D. P.

On the 3D Spatial Topologies of Local Molecular Clouds

- **47.** Speagle, J. S. et al. [18 additional co-authors], submitted to ApJ

 Mapping the Milky Way in 5-D with 170 Million Stars at High Galactic Latitudes
- **46. Speagle, J. S.** et al. [18 additional co-authors], submitted to **ApJ**Deriving Stellar Properties, Distances, and Reddenings from Photometry and Astrometry with brutus

Under Review

- 45. Emami, R.; Hernquist, L.; Alcock, C.; Genel, S.; Bose, S.; Weinberger, R.; Vogelsberger, M.; Shen, X.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Marinacci, F.; Forbes, J. C.; & Torrey, P.., submitted to **ApJ**Stellar Halo Morphology from TNG50: Twisted and Twisted-Stretched Halos
- 44. Bonaca, A.; Naidu, R. P.; Conroy, C.; Caldwell, N.; Cargile, P. A.; Han, J.; Johnson, B. D.; Kruijssen, J. M. D.; Myeong, G. C.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Ying, Y.-S.; & Zaritsky, D., submitted to **ApJL**

Orbital Clustering Identifies the Origins of Galactic Stellar Streams

- **43.** Johnson, B. D.; Leja, J.; Conroy, C.; & **Speagle**, **J. S.**, submitted to **ApJ** Stellar Population Inference with Prospector
- 42. Green, G. M.; Tschesche, L.; Rix, H.-W.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; Zucker, C.; Schlafly, E. F.; Rybizki, J.; & **Speagle, J. S.**, submitted to **ApJ**

Data-Driven Stellar Models

arxiv: 2006.16258

2020

41. Desprez, G. et al. [171 additional co-authors including **Speagle, J. S.**], **A&A**Euclid Preparation. X. The Euclid Photometric-Redshift Challenge

arxiv: 2009.12112

- 40. Carter, C.; Conroy, C.; Zaritsky, D.; Ting, Y.-S.; Bonaca, A.; Naidu, R. P.; Johnson, B. D.; Cargile, P. A.; Caldwell, N.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ

 Ancient Very Metal-Poor Stars Associated with the Galactic Disk in the H3 Survey
- 39. Zaritsky, D.; Conroy, C.; Naidu, R. P.; Cargile, P. A.; Putman, M.; Besla, G.; Bonaca, A.; Caldwell, N.; Han, J. J.; Johnson, B. D.; **Speagle, J. S.**; & Ting, Y.-S., **ApJL**Discovery of Magellanic Stellar Debris in the H3 Survey
- 38. Das, K. K.; Zucker, C.; Speagle, J. S.; Goodman, A.; Schlafly, E. F.; Green, G. M.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; & Alves, J., MNRAS

 Constraining the Distance to the North Polar Spur with Gaia DR2

 arxiv: 2009.01320
- 37. Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; Naidu, R. P.; Bonaca, A.; Zaritsky, D.; Ting, Y.-S.; Cargile, P. A.; Han, J. J.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ

 A Diffuse Metal-Poor Component of the Sagittarius Stream Revealed by the H3 Survey arxiv: 2007.14408
- Cargile, P. A.; Conroy, C.; Johnson, B. D.; Ting, Y.-S.; Bonaca, A.; Dotter, A.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ
 MINESweeper: Spectrophotometric Modeling of Stars in the Gaia Era arxiv: 1907.07690
- 35. Cabrera-Ziri, I.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Dalessandro, E.; Usher, C.; Bastian, N. J.; Salaris, M.; Martocchia, S.; Kozhurina-Platais, V.; Niederhofer, F.; Lardo, C.; & Larsen, S. S., **MNRAS**Searching for Globular Cluster Chemical Anomalies on the Main Sequence of a Young Massive Cluster arxiv: 2004.09636
- 34. Bonaca, A.; Conroy, C.; Hogg, D. W.; Cargile, P. A.; Caldwell, N.; Naidu, R. P.; Price-Whelan, A. M.; **Speagle, J. S.**; & Johnson, B. D., **ApJL**High-Resolution Spectroscopy of the GD-1 Stellar Stream Localizes the Perturber Near the Orbital Plane of Sagittarius

 arxiv: 2001.07215
- 33. Leja, J.; Speagle, J. S.; Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; van Dokkum, P.; & Franx, M., ApJ A New Census of the 0.2 < z < 3.0 Universe, Part I: The Stellar Mass Function arxiv: 1910.04168
- 32. Portillo, S. K. N. & Speagle, J. S.; & Finkbeiner, D. P., AJ

 Photometric Biases in Modern Surveys

 arxiv: 1902.02374

 Press: AAS
- 31. Speagle, J. S., MNRAS

 dynesty: A Dynamic Nested Sampling Package for Estimating Bayesian Posteriors and Evidences arxiv: 1904.02180
- 30. Alves, J.; Zucker, C.; Goodman, A. A.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Meingast, S.; Robitaille, T.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; Schlafly, E. F.; & Green, G. M., **Nature**Discovery of a Galactic-scale gas wave in the Solar Neighborhood

 arxiv: 2001.08748

Press: Official Website

29. Zucker, C.; Speagle, J. S.; Schlafly, E. F.; Green, G. M.; Finkbeiner, D. P., Goodman, A.; & Alves, J., A&A

A Compendium of Distances to Molecular Clouds in the Star Formation Handbook arxiv: 2001.00591

2019

28. Speagle, J. S., arxiv

A Conceptual Introduction to Markov Chain Monte Carlo Methods arxiv: 1909.12313

- 27. Green, G. M.; Schlafly, E. F.; Zucker, C.; Speagle, J. S.; & Finkbeiner, D. P., ApJ A 3D Dust Map Based on Gaia, Pan-STARRS 1 and 2MASS arxiv: 1905.02734
- 26. Huang, S.; Leauthaud, A.; Hearin, A.; Behroozi, P.; Bradshaw, C.; Ardila, F.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Tenenti, A.; Bundy, K.; Greene, J.; Sifón, C.; & Bahcall, N., **MNRAS**Weak Lensing Reveals a Tight Connection Between Dark Matter Halo Mass and the Distribution of Stellar Mass in Massive Galaxies
 arxiv: 1811.01139

Press: CfA Science Update

- 25. Speagle, J. S.; Leauthaud, A.; Huang, S.; Bradshaw, C. P.; Ardila, F.; Capak, P. L.; Eisenstein, D. J.; Masters, D. C.; Mandelbaum, R.; More, S.; Simet, M.; & Sifón, C., MNRAS Galaxy-Galaxy Lensing in HSC: Validation Tests and the Impact of Heterogeneous Spectroscopic Training Sets

 arxiv: 1906.05876
- 24. Namikawa, T. et al. [73 additional co-authors including **Speagle, J. S.**], **ApJ**Evidence for the Cross-correlation between Cosmic Microwave Background Polarization Lensing from POLARBEAR and the Cosmic Shear from Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam arxiv: 1904.02116
- 23. Forbes, J. C.; Krumholz, M. R.; & Speagle, J. S., MNRAS

 Towards a Radially-Resolved Semi-Analytic Model for the Evolution of Disc Galaxies Tuned with Machine Learning

 arxiv: 1810.12919
- 22. Cook, B. A.; Conroy, C.; van Dokkum, P.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ

 Measuring Star-Formation Histories, Distances, and Metallicities with Pixel Color-Magnitude

 Diagrams I: Model Definition and Mock Tests

 arxiv: 1904.00011
- 21. Safarzadeh, M.; Berger, E.; Leja, J.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJL

 Measuring the Delay Time Distribution of Binary Neutron Stars III. Using the Individual Star

 Formation Histories of Gravitational Wave Event Host Galaxies in the Local Universe

 arxiv: 1905.04310

 Press: AAS NOVA

- 20. Hikage, C. et al. [35 additional co-authors including **Speagle, J. S.**], **PASJ**Cosmology from cosmic shear power spectra with Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam first-year data arxiv: 1809.09148
- 19. Leja, J.; Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; van Dokkum, P.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Brammer, G.; Momcheva, I.; Skelton, R.; Whitaker, K. E.; Franx, M; & Nelson, E. J., **ApJ**An Older, More Quiescent Universe from Panchromatic SED Fitting of the 3D-HST Survey arxiv: 1812.05608
- 18. Zucker, C. & Speagle, J. S.; Schlafly, E. F.; Green, G. M., Finkbeiner, D. P.; Goodman, A. A.; & Alves, J., ApJ
 A Large Catalog of Accurate Distances to Local Molecular Clouds: The Gaia DR2 Edition arxiv: 1902.01425
- 17. Leja, J.; Carnall, A. C.; Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ How to Measure Galaxy Star Formation Histories II: Nonparametric Models arxiv: 1811.03637

2018

- Zucker, C.; Schlafly E. F.; Speagle, J. S.; Green, G. M.; Portillo, S. K. N.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; & Goodman, A. A., ApJ
 Mapping Distances Across the Perseus Molecular Cloud Using CO Observations, Stellar Photometry, and Gaia DR2 Parallax Measurements
 arxiv: 1803.08931
- 15. Medezinski, E.; Oguri, M.; Nishizawa, A.; Speagle, J. S.; Miyatake, H.; Umetsu, K.; Leauthaud, A.; Murata, R.; Mandelbaum, R.; Sifón, C.; Strauss, M. A.; Huang, S.; Simet, M.; Okabe, N.; Tanaka, M.; & Yutaka, K., PASJ

 Source Selection for Cluster Weak Lensing Measurements in the Hyper Sprime-Cam Survey arxiv: 1706.00427
- 14. Mandelbaum, R. et al. [30 additional co-authors including **Speagle, J. S.**], **PASJ**The first-year shear catalog of the Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam SSP Survey arxiv: 1706.06745
- Tanaka, M.; Coupon, J.; Hsieh, B.-C.; Mineo, S., Nishizawa, A. J.; Speagle, J.; Furusawa, H.; Miyazaki, S.; & Murayama, H., PASJ

 Photometric Redshifts for the Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program Data Release 1
 arxiv: 1704.05988
- 12. Aihara, H. et al. [108 additional co-authors including **Speagle, J. S.**], **PASJ**First Data Release of the Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program

 arxiv: 1702.08449
- 11. Aihara, H. et al. [142 additional co-authors including **Speagle, J. S.**], **PASJ**The Hyper Suprime-Cam SSP Survey: Overview and Survey Design arxiv: 1704.05858
- 10. Oguri, M. et al. [24 additional co-authors including Speagle, J. S.], PASJ

An optically-selected cluster catalog at redshift 0.1<z<1.1 from Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic

Program S16A data arxiv: 1701.00818

2017

9. Speagle, J. S. & Eisenstein, D. J., MNRAS

Deriving Photometric Redshifts with Fuzzy Archetypes and Self-Organizing Maps II. Implementation arxiv: 1510.08080

8. Speagle, J. S. & Eisenstein, D. J., MNRAS

Deriving Photometric Redshifts with Fuzzy Archetypes and Self-Organizing Maps I. Methodology arxiv: 1510.08073

2016

7. Speagle, J. S.; Capak, P. L.; Eisenstein, D. J.; Masters, D. C.; Steinhardt, C. L., MNRAS

Exploring Photometric Redshifts as an Optimization Problem: An Ensemble MCMC and Simulated

Annealing-Driven Template-fitting Approach

arxiv: 1508.02484

6. Steinhardt, C. L.; Capak, P. L.; Masters, D. C.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ The Impossibly Early Galaxy Problem

arxiv: <u>1506.01377</u>

2015

5. Masters, D. C. et al. [19 additional co-authors including **Speagle, J. S.**], **ApJ**Mapping the Galaxy Color-Redshift Relation: Optimal Photometric Redshift Calibration Strategies for Cosmology Surveys

arxiv: 1509.03318

2014

4. Steinhardt, C. L. & Speagle, J. S., ApJ

A Uniform History for Galaxy Evolution

arxiv: 1409.2883

3. Steinhardt, C. L.; Speagle, J. S. et al. [22 additional co-authors], ApJL Star Formation at 4 < z < 6 from the Spitzer Large Area Survey with Hyper-Suprime-Cam (SPLASH)

arxiv: <u>1407.7030</u>

Press: JPL

2. Speagle, J. S.; Steinhardt, C. L.; Capak, P. L.; & Silverman, J. D., ApJS

A Highly Consistent Framework for the Evolution of the Star-Forming 'Main Sequence' from z~0-6 arxiv: 1405.2041

1. Speagle, J. S.; Kaplan, D. L.; & van Kerkwijk, M. H., ApJ The X-ray Counterpart of the High-B Pulsar J0726-2612 arxiv: 1111.2877